so the three things that are happening
in that video one is Stewart Kaufman's
the adjacent possible
the second is Greg's tree of knowledge
yeah and the the third is the the
inquiry
since bunny so Daniel smacking burger
now I've been going back and forth on
the inquiry of what is the battery I'm
gonna have to explain what I mean by
this but what's the battery of a cydia
right and and the way when I put that
question to him I said look one of the
moments of genius of Elaan musk one of
the many but one of the most I think
central is the call a strategic grasp of
Moore's law and so it would the the the
battery which is to say energy density
per dollar specifically the
technological complex which right now
shows that there's lithium-ion batteries
has this characteristic in the context
of the electric motor so someone like
these two relationships you that the
electric motor which is like a
fundamental architecture then you've got
the the battery which is the rate limit
on the potential of that fundamental
architecture right and you've got the
series of step functions or trophic
cascades and with what must grasp was
that there's a way to order things such
that the larger milieu in this case
capitalism will orient activity to
exploring the adjacent possible in
battery space up to some limit and if
you if you if you get to a particular
location which is the Tesla Roadster you
can combine the power density over
dollar of a battery space at that moment
with the electric motor to produce a
change a feedback loop back into
capitalism
which generates more resource allocation
like we're money fund R&D in exploring
battery space which because battery
spaces on this Moore's law and an
ethical point is on this moore's law
gets you on some form of exponential
growth or in this case exponential
decline in cost depending on your
preference so a for example at $1,000
per kilowatt hour the only thing that is
marketable at all is the tesla roadster
it is very very narrow territory right
once the Tesla Roadster hits it
generates enough for resources to then
move batteries along there Moore's Law
curve to the point where in call it 18
months doesn't matter it has so $500 per
kilowatt hour but $500 per kilowatt hour
now notion rate then own little machines
right right but now you could do the
Tesla Model S which is a hundred times
more market space like the volume of
that market space is a hundred times
larger than the most maybe even a
thousand times maybe sing sort of some
attitude which then recursively
generates another flow of resources that
allows you to do the work necessary the
what's it called in calculus language
it's the the thermodynamic cycle the
thermodynamic neighbor it provides the
resources necessary to do the
thermodynamic labor to explore the
adjacent possible in battery space to
then move you to the next step function
in Moore's law which is then $250 per
kilowatt hour which then unlocks the
model three which is you know call it
six orders of magnitude more marker
marketability you get this series of
feedback loop so it's actually like a so
it's funny the the actual electric
engine in this case is actually a
metaphor for a tap engine adjacent
possible engine and then what Greg talks
about is greg actually talks about if
you just zoom out and you take a look at
the kind of the macro story of what the
Moore's Law face of the tap engine looks
like right with me on this yeah you can
actually start getting a genuine just
the same way the ELA must look at
at the battery and the Moore's law sort
of capitalism's thing you can actually
get a similar invisibility okay so we
went from matter to life to behavior to
culture and each one is a series of
moves in this in this in this tap
Moore's law right and and we can now
think about how do we actually design a
tap engine that moves us along that
particular Moore's Law and that's the
the generator functions of hard obsidium
Wow that's very cool
that's very cool I like that so you know
that Greg and I have been in constant
dialogue as well right you need to that
yes exactly because he's he and I have
been doing two things we've been
integrating sort of theory of knowledge
with relevance realization theory which
he sees as the two are deeply
interpenetrating and that thing you just
described that art is of course it's a
metaphysical extension of in Thompson's
idea of deep continuity in cognition all
the way down and all the way up vision
and that's the that's a connection that
Greg sees between theory of knowledge
and relevance realization and deep
continuity and then Greg and I are now
actually doing a series together we've
actually filmed a couple of episodes
where we are doing what's called
untangling the world not of
consciousness the hard problems of mind
and meaning we're going through an
extensive argument I built about trying
to get naturalistic account of
consciousness and you can see how that
then plugs into his tree of knowledge
model as well so it might be a good idea
if the three of us actually spoke at
some time I think it's it's definitely
the next step the next definitely but
you get to three of us and I'm wondering
it's not I don't think it's just ready
yet but I definitely see somebody like
Zach Stein as being in that next wave
and maybe maybe Chris like there's
something there yes I mean yeah you know
exact and I just filmed another
conversation with Andrew Sweeney so Zach
and I have also built up very powerful
momentum we've gotten into a discussion
about the meta political which i think
is a very interesting discussion that
doc and I are having and and that
strikes me as part of what the cultural
side of the city and is also trying to
address so again it shouldn't work a
couple complemented by mentation up
thank you something I'm sorry I cure the
dawn did a meaning wave arounds steal
the culture and then he and I had a
discussion on the snow about it and I
mentioned your work on the Scythian in
that discussion so I'll have to see that
meaning lake yeah yeah he's a very
interesting character in this in this
story yeah very much it was it was it
was a pleasure and talking about that
whole notion was really cool
because I thought that I presented the
argument that I think there's deep
consonants between the project of trying
to steal the culture and the project of
trying to bring about something like the
sibian I think those two are deeply
connect well okay so having having
having not wash that dialogue let me
throw some things in there so that first
I guess maybe I'm kind of loading my a
cure the dawn like simulator so playful
words so you know the color I was like
yeah like steal the coach like to stew
to make the culture stronger to Neal
culture and and so there so here's the
visual image this is the pin that's been
keeps popping into my head well probably
should I'll try the visual image I just
got even more visual in my conversation
it's Greg it's like okay so we have the
example of the discovery in complex
chemistry space the very specific
complex the very specific architecture
that includes things like DNA RNA and
cell membranes so there's some some some
specific very specific architecture that
includes these aspects of complex
chemistry that are naturally occurring
in complex chemistry space that when
arranged in a very precise way generate
a portal
which is to say generate a an enormous
Lee asymmetric shift in the probability
landscape mm-hmm
which then creates the opening into the
next four that's the whole talk thing
right that look so this is the
Aristotelian idea that living things can
do things and can actualize matter in a
way that inorganic processors never can
I mean with the idea that it's what's
happening is ultimately they reinvent
you of the of Aristotle's notions which
i think is right and so people in the
philosophy of biology are talking about
this in terms of closure of constraints
not only do you have constraints closing
feedback cite both in life you have
constraints through that form a
systematic closure with respect to each
other they're all me so the constraints
are not only downward against not only
constraining the feedbacks like those
the constraints are also locked together
in becoming mutually interdependent with
each other exactly exactly exactly yeah
when I said architecture that what I was
referring to as that notion of the the
inter locking mesh of constraints that
hold it straight complex into a into
something like any of that and that
that's powerful language because when
you move to the talking about that kind
of architecture of constraints you can
see why it makes accessible you Jason
possible because constraints are exactly
the shaping of possibility right and
that gives you sort of a more clearer
explanation of why it moves while you
get that change in chef yeah yeah
exactly okay so cool so take that
particularly anybody happens to be
holding that very clearly and then apply
that to culture space yes so true to -
mr. Truman is using recapture the
culture Oh steal the culture yeah the
term I used a moment ago was reinvent oh
I picked up on the Latin word invent EO
from carries book because inventio means
it falls between two words that we put
in opposition it means both to discover
and to make inventio yes yes there we go
yeah
yeah so so so the the the if you if you
sort of compared those two what happens
is or a way of saying what what you're
saying in this in this other language is
to discover and or invent inventio the
set of downward and interoperating
constraints that select from culture
space that particular precise culture
that is the moral equivalent of DNA RNA
and cell membranes I hope that that's
what I'm trying that I think that's the
analogy I was using when I was talking
to a hero and that actually came from an
earlier thing I said when I was on the
snow I answered the question the analogy
I use is the way Christianity stole the
culture that it wasn't a political
revolution attempting to overturn the
regime what it was was a bottom-up
creation of an alternative culture that
event shuri right that is largely
ignored and then oppressed but then
eventually basically becomes the basis
of a new civilization in the medieval
period and that's what I mean about what
I what I'm what I'm trying to facilitate
with my work yeah great exactly so you
can say is there's something that is I'm
gonna use the term generator function
probably not very well but I'm trying to
represent the selection or the set of
constraints in the movie we were just
describing it which is as meta to
actually transcend into the actuals of
the given culture yes exactly exactly so
Christianity operates as a new
transcendent a new generator function in
culture space that's selected from the
milieu that was available in Rome which
of course is very large rich / rich
because an adjacent possible is actually
over overwhelmingly large selects a
particular subset of that into what then
becomes a culture that has
characteristics that are more adaptive
in the context of the decline of Rome
yes and they make possible new ways of
being I mean some carries book where I
got the term inventio from basically
argues that Augustine crafts our notion
of the interior self
and of course you get Christian the
Christianity promotion of ideas of agape
and all kinds of new ways of being and
these have huge cultural consequences
and socio-political consequences this is
part of Tom Hollands argument right that
you know Christianity makes infanticide
a moral crime whereas previously
infanticide is an accepted practice we
are now so infiltrated by this that it
to use Frank words term it's not a lot
of option for us we can imagine it and
infer it but it would be like but for
none of us do we could we bring
ourselves to get to that state of
interior agency and external you know
participation where that would be a
viable alternative for us and so that
that's that's what I'm that's what I'm
hearing when you're saying how it's
possible they to move to the adjacent
possible I'm connecting that to
Frankfurt's notion of going from things
that are abstract possibilities to
viable options for people that that's
the actual cognitive move that's
happening what we're talking about this
yeah okay so what I'm seeing there is
something like I guess it looks a little
bit like a rhizome a little bit like a
kind of a branching or capillary system
right and they're they growing towards
or becoming more adjacent to and then a
critical energy so I've got a person and
I've got a location in culture space and
I've got a distance that they're they're
ready willing and able to go right and
as as the rhizome as the capillary
structure of of culture branches until
it gets within that critical distance
then they will migrate right they will
make the move to get on to that
particular branch and I would make it a
little bit more biological in that I
would make it more like each
construction that right there moving is
also helping to draw right right like
it's like it's like the organism
environment each construction model I
think that's so I see yeah that people
are doing it
niche construct
the way in which that sort of evolves
into existence right and so this is like
this is the this is South we're
describing here sort of the meta
constraint on the generator function
right and any viable generative fraction
has to look like that and then we apply
the this is doing the stuff you and Greg
are sort of the reason why you're the
right people would be doing this is that
we then apply the our best understanding
of the actual context yes where are the
actual designs of cultural milieu that
are highly in alignment with the best
ways for people to you know feel seen
and to activate their highest potential
all that other kinds of stuff right if
you can
that's what about if you say that any
any culture we're simultaneously any
person will feel like they are more well
met they're living their well-being is
going they feel like they're mobbing is
going up by participating in it and it
is so designed that their participation
increases the global capacity of that
culture to up gradient the well-being of
every member of that culture that's sort
of mathematically the hard part is doing
it but mathematically that's what you're
looking to do and back just to kind of
find it and the point or the proposition
is is that that language and the
language of the portal pathway or the
cell membrane DNA are in a location
precise location and culture space like
those are the same yes there are two
different ways of talking about the same
kind of thing so I like all of that I
look but I have a potential addendum or
maybe you're saying this and I just
haven't seen seen it imply I think what
happens in these transitions is not only
and and maybe you mean this by upgrade
it's not just a qualitative change I'm
sorry it's not just a quantity the
quantitative change in well-being it's
not like the Christians felt like they
had with the Roman elite had but just
more they've got the field of human
existence and experience had been
widened qualitatively not just a
quantitative expansion yeah yeah so so
let's hit this tone I don't think I've
actually done this yet out loud so we'll
just this is great to have this here so
tyson yoko puerta the san talk i
recommend his book recently
so I'm gonna be referencing his stuff a
lot and I imagine that at some point not
too long from now we'll also be getting
into relationship but he makes a really
good distinction from an indigenous
knowing respect but very good
distinction between growth and increase
right talk about in the context of
economics but for example if I want to
get smarter I mean a broad brush I want
to get to the details I want to get to
smarter I've got basically two basic
approaches I can either grow the node
the size of my brain I can add more
neurons just get a bigger brain and
that's a little bit like saying I'm
gonna grow GDP I'm just gonna kind of
add more piles of gold to the to the
pieces of gold to the pile of gold that
I've got or I can I can increase the
quality of relationships of neurons I
can increase the quality of synaptic and
connections and so he you know his
pointers is high his proposition is that
broadly speaking civilization or more
narrowly capitalism has a growth model
it wants to just add more neurons yes
where the indigenous approach and we
will just preserve the pose the approach
that you were just describing in the
context of the right answer to culture
space is this increased approach yes and
that's what was central and Aristotle
right an animal is not just more of a
plant and animal can do things it's
animate it can move around and explore
the environment in ways that are
qualitatively different and my
international beings can explore
conceptual space in a way that merely
animated beings cannot etc that's the
qualitative thing that's very very
central right right so let's suppose I'm
gonna make that I'm gonna head double
click on that so two moves and stick em
on remember put my thumb up here's a
mnemonic to remember but secondly
because so the first move ever return
this back to the notion of Sevilla all
the way back to the very first video in
the city of Ceres hua is if I take a
look at Metcalfe's law went to thing
that thing that drives cities to become
vast Metcalf slog really just talking
about the size and the adjacent possible
I think the size of impossibility space
and the number of possible relationships
I actually talking about growth if I add
another person I grow the number of
possible relationships if it's another
thing over here which I'm gonna call you
a capper toes law which has to do with
the how do you go about actually
selecting from the possible the actual
relationships and which is a qualitative
question not a quantitative question do
I increase the quality of relationality
inside the zone of possibility you can
think of it just like Facebook right
there's a an arbitrarily large number of
possible places but which ones do you
actually have and in that context there
seems to be three primary variables one
variable is sin sin since the who like
do I talk with do I know John do I know
Greg who there's a billion people out
there what tiny tiny subset of that are
the ones I'm going to have relationship
with at all the second one is in some
sense the what so now that I'm in
relationship with John now what's the
orienting basis of what aspect of that
large possibilities because of just our
relationship that we're focusing on and
then in some sense there's the how which
is to say what is our capacity as
individuals in all the ways like our
capacity to communicate our capacity to
emotional regulate you know our capacity
to collaborate all that skillfulness of
being in relationship that you know
grabs as much of the sphere of
possibility in the relationship as we
can and so if I think about all three of
those characteristics so I can
consistently work toward generating a
network reddit community a set of
relationships that has as its back to
the kind of Moore's Law battering
feedback loop as it has its surplus
value as a generative result every move
in the network like increasing the
quality it increases those three
characteristics so each sort of day the
Congress the relationships are my
entering into our are better or higher
quality set of relationships the the
scope the thing that is happening in the
context of those relationships is the
most what is called for in that moment
and the people in relationship are
getting better and better and better at
actually being in relationship right so
that that creates a series of feedback
loops that has this this movement that's
that's qualitative that's focused on the
qualitative level one focus on
qualitative level
- is this thing where we say okay okay
the aristotelian piece would you say
okay once you've done that once you've
been able to make this move we are
actually sort of designing culture
around those three variables and finding
a way to hold the network so that it is
always up gradient across that that that
direction you've now done the transition
where you've moved basically that's the
last move in culture space and in the
same sense that organic you know
genetics was the last move in complex
chemistry space and that culture was the
last move in behavior space I'm
referring to talk so that's the last
move in culture space which unlocks
this whole new territory about which we
can only say a little bit right we can
say some things we can't actually say a
lot about what the affordances that are
perhaps even novel there's something
that happens in this post cultural
domain and I don't mean post in the
sense the culture is left behind I mean
post in the sense that is actually what
happens when you kind of get cultured
dial in so that you can you can actually
radically change the probability of
what's it's what you can so radically
change the probability landscape of what
is generated by culture you can actually
not begin to build on top of it a whole
new layer of stuff again in the same way
the culture sits on top of a narrow band
of mind and mind sits on top of a narrow
band of life and life systems up the
narrow band of chemistry so that's like
mode one is focusing on optimizing for
the qualitative characteristics of this
met caste law dynamic mode two is once
you've got that dialed in you can
basically figure out what's the was the
way you describe the set of constraints
that hold that thing together so each
iteration is always an upgrade Ian on
the previous iteration then you've got a
pop into this next portal papri so that
sounds very much like and I mean this is
a compliment that sounds very much like
a cultural or a distributed cognition
analog to the kind of metaphysics that
Aristotle's building in his account so
I'm wondering if that analog hole
a question emerges it strikes me that
there was a fourth you did the who what
and how but Aristotle also has a why and
she is there's an emergent phenomena
Lachie of normativity that right the
that's what I meant about a volatile
change in well-being what it is for a
plant to be good is deeply unsatisfying
to me or for an animal to be good and
what it is for an animal to be good or
to have a good life it's deeply
unsatisfying to me as a rational agent
yeah right and so what happened so you
start to move up from survival to power
to truth right and right and so you get
one one marker of an emergent space of
viable adjacent possibility is an
emergent lived new normativity and I
don't mean a new moral rule I mean a new
moral principle but our new normative
principle perhaps morals too
I don't mind it's more like mean
epistemic and aesthetic right and
perhaps beyond but some new normativity
is emerging and again it's not merging
and merging it's not I'm not saying but
a new set of rules I'm talking about the
way in which we judge the value of
things is the point here and the reason
why as challenges is we probably can't
say much about it amazing saying isn't
even even going to be the right tool you
know saying is kind of a cultural tool
but if you did the metaphor works right
if I say okay I've got a I've got a kind
of a Y space a sense end value domain
that is appropriate to the level of
plans and you know what it means to live
a good life at the level of plants is
deeply unsatisfying to to you and plants
have no real ability to relate to the
set of values and sense that you have
that's right and the proposition is that
if we dial this thing in at the level of
culture we enter into a new mill you
about which we can say only that it
stands in relationship to culture in the
way the culture or humans stand in
relationship to plants you can say that
it will vastly and the word vast isn't
even a big enough word we need some I'm
gonna have to it's happened to your
vocabulary super double plus vastly
Greece's whitespace increases the the
domain of sense and value at a level
that would leave you know 20th century
humans certainly but your us kind of
going like kind of shrug it's just like
this it's a it's a we can't use ordinary
cognition or language to refer to it in
just the same way that a plant can't use
ordinary planting to refer to the
well-being of a human okay so so let's
use a historical analog for that because
I've used this argument in in awakening
for the meaning crisis we can we do not
and I don't need propositional e I mean
at this level of phenomenological
normativity we cannot identify with the
pre actual world right we it's not a la
it's not a livable option for us I can
learn all kinds of propositions and make
inferences and come up with excellent
theories about the Egyptians and the
world but they're not they're not I
don't identify with them I'm not it I'm
not it's not keeper well and that's to
me analogous to what you're talking
about
there's a cultural organization in the
Bronze Age and it moves in a continuous
cosmos a very different normativity
space than one we have now and then what
that speaks to me if that so I'm
building an analogy on an analogy so
this is getting precarious epistemic Lee
I acknowledge that right here right now
but we're friends and we're playing with
ideas right what I what I look for is
and of course what's happening right is
you get a fundamental socio-cultural
organize reorganization right and the
place I see where people play with the
emerging normativity and and inventio it
they're both discovering it and
inventing it in in connection to how
this is coming both is of course you
know the emergence of fundamentally do
new religions that and and that was a
that was that was you know you get the
emergence of all the and notice what the
actual age religions do they wait they
create these universal religions that
put us in a much different normativity
space than we ever were in the pre axial
world
and so what I've taken that as an
argument to me to be able and in
connection with stealing the culture is
to try and look at sort of the meta
processes that help might facilitate the
birth of you know a new religion spoken
grandiosely hence the religion that's
the project of the religion that's not a
religion and most importantly the whole
project of dialectic India logos as the
place is trying to create a virtual
engine in which that machinery of
playing with emergent phenomenon
emergent phenomenology of normativity is
action taking place and you you were on
my discipline server there are
communities out there that are playing
with this mm-hmm right now they're
playing with this right now
yeah and just to I mean it seems like an
opportunity right now to do a little bit
of clarification because I know that the
the languaging of religion and
languaging the religion is not a
religion is oftentimes confusing yes and
I mean it's kind of hyper confusing
because we live at the tail end of a war
where science declared rhetorical war on
on religion because I had to and it's
kind of smeared and confused the name so
what I believe we mean by the reference
to the term religion is a little is very
much like this this metaphor of DNA RNA
and some membrane but that's my point
what religion means is going to go
through that kind of shift like it's
going to be qualitatively different
right probably maybe different exactly
right but if you compare religion after
yet to revolution to religion before
that's what I'm talking about it's not
like new proposition it's the me the
very meaning of what it was and what
wisdom is and what meaning like oh and
they eat what the transcendent if all of
that had undergone a fundamental change
that's what I'm talking about right
exactly so when we talk about what this
is other than this next thing looks like
we have to become super abstract to be
able to say okay is there a continuity
if there is there a company there's
transformation there's change is there
any sense of continuity that allows us
to use the same word to refer to them at
all or something using a different word
and I believe there is actually
continuity but
it was something like some interlocking
intermesh set of constraints I think so
I mean I mean so Evans take on an update
of Aristotle is called the deep
continuity hypothesis and it's the idea
that there you know that there's there's
well first I'll say how I think he takes
it and then my interpretation of it and
I don't want those confuse because he
might not agree with the second thing so
the point about deep continuity from
Aristotle is you know it's not like it's
not a ladder
the animal doesn't leave all of the
principles and patterns of the plant
behind right but it builds on them and
this is your DNA metaphor it scaffolds
on them right new machinery that allows
new things and so how Evans sort of
tends to present it is you know there's
both identity and difference when we
talk about deep continuity and both are
important the way I've tried to
understand that is with the evolutionary
metaphor of exaptation
because in upset patient it's not like I
sew my tongue there's continuity between
the tongue that masticates and tastes
and the tongue that speaks but that
doesn't mean the taste and speech are
identical and so that that and so I
think my whole my theoretical hope is
that in this one's I think what Greg and
I are groping towards is that the
machinery of things like relevance
realization and religio is the thing
that's going to go through some kind of
excitation in there yeah exactly so
perfect so it's almost like a mmm I
don't see two sides of a coin or two
sides of the mirror because there's -
there's like a two side so the tongue
the tongue that speaks must also be the
tongue that tastes yes yes dispense with
the prior you you must maintain so you
think like animals so animals and plants
well there's a there needs to be some
way of bringing in resources from the
outside there needs to be some way of
copying and high-fidelity replication of
the construct but there's a whole set of
things that are the same between plants
and animals yes it will do as animals do
two things right one is they satisfy the
requirements that are that are the
shared requirements of plants and
animals in a way right but then unlocks
a whole new me whole new milieu all new
possibility space which to say this they
exact they they again you can say that
it's funny animal is actually a
particular solution to organism yes I
know and it's a particular solution to
organism which by the way is is is
radically dependent on plant yeah as
part of its input as part of his complex
and by virtue of solving or the organism
problem in a particular way unlocks this
exact of potential which is the new
milieu yeah beautifully said beautifully
said exactly what I wanted to convey so
this thing / that's not true
our Fortran are trying to feel this
feels very brew we don't have the
imbalance between them it has the same
thing right on the one hand sort of
downward facing or inward facing your
past facing it's a it's a solution to
culture space and solution to religion
space yeah that is sits alongside all
the other solutions to culture and
religion space in a particular way but
it does so in a fashion and probably by
the way in a fashion which is dependent
upon many other right yeah it unlocks a
new executive potential and then zapped
of potential has a whole set of
qualities or affordances like from you
know a dog eats but it is a dog does not
does not sing it vocalising it does not
sing same thing right the curve crap you
know solve the problem of religion space
but it opens up this new just new milieu
and this milieu is one in which we
currently can't we can't even we could
just kind of point at it because my
definition until it happens it ain't
happened and we can't know what's gonna
be in there
right I that was beautifully said what
I'm adding to that and I think you're
you are to in practice is I feel a moral
imperative to try and figure out and
this is pragmatic like it's not we're
facing a transformative experience in
the LA Paul sense we don't
what its gonna be like until we're on
the other side again but you know but as
I've argued serious play is the best
thing we have in the face of nation and
my moral imperative is how can I best
facilitate the conditions of that
serious play that have the most current
fallible plausibility that I will help
to afford that acceptation that we're
talking about that's that sort of the
project I'm really wrestling with right
now mm-hmm
yeah that's neat yeah and the word
serious play you can I find myself
called to the play side yeah just say
okay you know hey guys check this out
like all the cool things you ever heard
of or ever thought of or ever dreamed of
every super cool thing that's everybody
tractive in the entire history of all
culture that is below the curve of
what's on the other side of this thing
yeah so how do you do it so if you if
you like we my thing about sort of the
the moral the combat like the you know
the that sense of being called let's put
it that way that sense of being called
to try and facilitate that that so what
what does that what does that mean
though sort of tactically do you think I
say that again okay
so we're we like so I don't wanna put
words in your mouth
so I'll just speak from right -
perspective I see myself as right and
when I use the word pragmatic I use it
like in the you know in the James Ian
you know I'm using it in an effective
logical sense right yeah so I want to do
my sort of pragmatic best to facilitate
figure out the conditions of serious
play that are most likely to afford
people to exact without falling into the
usual trope of a utopia yeah okay cool
came for me as you were saying that is
something like what does it feel like to
be called to singing when the tongue has
yet only known taste right right it's
like that lab you'll experimentation of
the discovery of a like we're right next
to singing this right we're almost like
there's like this kind of experimental
like lurching into and like this
cracking and croaking like this
coordination between the voice box and
the lungs and the lips and the tongue is
funny actually new you watch the child
learning how to whistle
yeah like that right there's it ah
there's something there man I could
fucking feel it it's almost but all I
can do is like sometimes pucker my mouth
and blow but it's not quite coming
through yes that's the place right so
it's important to recognize that's the
place you know check this shit out how
does it a good metaphor utopianism is
when a kid does this things like
three-year-old I just like I was
whistling and then I hung that's
utopianism utopianism is what happens
when you fake it when you try to
simulate the reality that we can kind of
sense it's right over there if we just
kind of get to all the right pieces
together in the right way to generate
possibility that we can sense like we
can sense that possibility in something
like oh man it's just almost there
and utopianism is faking it okay so one
don't fake it don't don't pretend that
you're doing something you're not doing
yeah and recognize that there's you know
it's it's a it's practice there's a
there's a practice and that practices
this really interesting practice that
happens in a certain mode or it happens
motive of serious play yeah what one of
the things I actually did during the
sort of the most quarantined period of
this this last few months was pick what
are life skills that I have always been
interested in getting that I never spent
the time getting cuz I got time what am
i I do so I focused on this whistle the
two fingers in mouth still not there so
I can kind of do it and so I actually
had
Zach experienced it like okay hold on
like this and that that kind of expect
you have to be the very experimental
Millia to try different things and play
that go forth and and and yet here's the
trick this is the thing that I think is
like hammer on on steel the orienting
basis of the subtle awareness of the
directionality towards getting it right
yes well this supposed to worsen the
faith's not we've been talking about I
think yes yes so this was unify it's
it's the it's the the thing that is
searching inside the spaces of adjacent
possible I think about just this problem
how do i whistle you know all I did is
trying to do a combinatorial across all
the different configurations available
there no fucking way
right you're the inner problem there's
some way to to have access to a set of
constraints that radically radically
constrained like 1 times 10 to the 120
constrain the configurations in the
possibility space such that it actually
is something that I can then begin to
operate within and so there's something
there right there's something like you
said there's some mode something that we
have yes
back that we can use to notice or do
something around that constraint
characteristic and then something that
we have to be able to explore within the
boundaries of that constraint
characteristic okay big too big
hmm okay well there's let me go back you
you hit the nail you hit this now
probably more resoundingly than anybody
I've ever met which is well that
something is definitely not
propositional yes that something is
something that has to by definition take
into account and take advantage of the
whole lineage of the universe from the
beginning until the moment you were
right now it doesn't leverage all of it
and the best of it it's definitely not
gonna get the job done yeah
so let's not take a narrow slice through
like a particular subset of that hole
that was super interesting in the 1950s
and just do that let's actually really
think about how we grasp the whole of
reality as
as we can and bring it to bear in this
particular problem to me yes I agree
with that totally ha this is where Greg
stuff gets extremely mystical very
quickly what's he call like the Sun a la
pintura something like that yeah
but it's not a bad metaphor right I mean
in some sense what we were just talking
about is that each of us then is a
particular I worst singer aspect of that
whole and in continuity with that whole
so there's a way in which this story of
the coordination or the coherence of
this network this group of singular
beings people is the whole which is to
say the whole of reality or at least
quantum of the whole of reality to that
particular distributed cognition
contains doing its thing right becoming
operant on itself I think that's right I
mean and that's that could that in a
sense completes that our STARTTLS model
because what you get at the highest
level for in his model human beings I
mean the gods are above it but they're
not in they're not in there they're not
in the analysis is at every previous
level you have machinery of
actualization right so the plant
actualizes a particular potential in
organic manner that couldn't be
actualized before right and then the
animal actualized as a potential in that
in in vegetative existence that couldn't
be actualized before and then you get
the right and then you get what you
might call the cognitive agent that
actualizes but then at the top of it is
the rational agent and what the rational
agent does is they appropriate actual
light that actualization as a kind of
self actualization the actualization
process becomes recursively self
actualizing
in the rational being because i being is
aware of all of the other and can bring
that and can bring that into its
processing in a way that a plant can't
an animal can't or a merely cognitive
being I can't exactly this is what that
bending the curve right that's that's
the the deepest sense of that notion of
the singularity that folks have hit on
yeah because once you have
the capacity to utilize actualization to
increase the capacity to actualize yes
looks like you know n is one either the
the exponent is anything super linear
yeah anything superlinear then it goes
like that
another way of saying the same the same
thing but important G's so so oh wait so
so this is this is crucial so this is a
just landed I just want me the animal
does not dispense with the plant or the
plant does not dispense with chemistry
actually occur does not dispense with
social animals that's right
this threshold that we're talking about
it does not dispense with culture does
not dispense with humans it's not just
animals there's no suspense right it
actually the whole point is that it
maintains the continuity integrity of
that entire substrate that's right
that's right and that's why it's better
to think of it along the metaphor of
excitation rather than the metaphor of
revolution yes very nice very nice and
this so judge turtle and we had this
really beautiful story that has a
characteristic of like when we arrived
we arrived both at a location that we
will acknowledge we will feel is fully
harmonious with our highest senses it
will seem it will feel and appear to be
of both the highest value and the most
highest truth of which we can be aware
right it'll be awesome awesome it'll be
awesome in the instead of the banal
sense and then also right simultaneously
it will be awesome in in the deeper
sense will open us up into a whole new
gig about you know again about which we
can say very little right now and it but
but we can say that that the awesome in
the deeper sense will always be self
consciously aware crucially self
consciously aware of the necessity of
its maintaining the integrity of the
awesome in the more banal sense in
perpetuity or these for a very long time
that's very good
when you sit when you were saying that
what came to mind is Paul and from
Corinthians at the end of the hymn -
agape for now we see as in a mirror
darkly but then we shall know even at we
shall know fully even as we are fully
known
he saw Christianity as exactly the
serious play of agape and right now we
only see in a mirror darkly but it will
bring us somehow to the place where we
will see fully even as we are fully
known
so that vision was actually part of his
way of understanding the cultural
excitation that he was he dedicated his
life to trying to bring about in this
weird circle of my own autobiography I'm
feeling more and more affinity with st.
Paul who was always a deeply ambivalent
figure for me given my own particular
religious upbringing but I now
appreciate more what he was trying to
articulate in fact that was perhaps the
best thing to have said I think you get
the wonderful him from agape which is
the new way of being but he doesn't
claim and now we're in Utopia in fact he
says but now we see in a mirror darkly
notice it's a reflection and its shadow
but that bad act of constantly loving in
that way and looking in that mirror that
reflection will actually bring us to the
place we where we fully know even as we
are fully knowing which is a very
transductive way of putting this kind of
thing I think you're talking about it's
just it's a similar kind of vision and I
just thought that was a beautiful in it
bear well maybe the same vision as far
as I can tell yeah maybe like like we
talked about the mission that
transcendent operator we talked about
the notion of continuity it least seems
plausible that there is a there's a sort
of a deep continuity I think I just
copied the title with a transcendent
operator capital T yes very much
and in which case it is the same vision
yeah I think this goes towards the work
Chris and Andrew and I have been doing
it's a sort of the reinventing of the
notion of soul as that which by now
we mediates between more nests and
suchness continuously and so yeah we're
the suchness is you know the the the the
non categorical determinate miss of your
being which of course is a product of
all of your historicity and of all of
the stacks from the participant from the
inorganic all the way up through the
participatory all the way up but then
the morning is exactly what you're
talking about that relationship to right
the indefinite possibility that is
nevertheless not homogeneous ly
indefinite it has some you know nascent
structure that we by serious play we are
affording its emerging intelligibility
to us that's what I'm trying to do with
the the seeing in the mirror darkly kind
of idea yeah so maybe just the last
thing to put on this color noticing my
I'm definitely running out of energy I
mean this has been great I'm so glad to
be able to get back into into the flow
with you and I look forward to you me
and Greg having a conversation yes
getting I can I noticed that my health
is up into the right I can cycles but
it's up and to the right so it's it's
close I'll give you the last word but I
also wanted to say I'm also really
enjoying this again with you yeah so the
the thing that was coming into my mind I
guess having this sort of movie play in
the back of my mind as you're talking I
don't know if you've if you've seen the
video that I did about Oceanics it's the
most recent Scythian video and you can
just look at those units as a thing but
it's it's a vision a very practical this
is a key the point is practical it's a
vision of a way of living
like literally hexagons floating on the
ocean coordinating particular ways but
you know at the engineering level having
thought through a whole bunch of stops
the ability to do like closed-loop water
or closed-loop food clothes with energy
production like a migration of a period
of generations I don't mean human
generations I mean in a bit of
generations where they can actually
begin to produce themselves without you
know imports of foreign materials and
reducing extra nowness I could say very
Pratt
tickle imagination of a way of living
that is well in some sense would feel
pretty fucking utopian like a whole lot
better so let's just put a whole lot
better by no means even intending to
believe itself as being the end point
but a step function like a whole step if
you think about like 19th sand the 19th
century way of living that we happen to
the narrated sort of weird ramshackle
glue elevators to cars and boom
and try not to die too quickly it's like
a whole bunch better than that right and
it's like right now we're those guys
I've been talking to them quite
extensively they had the architectural
design to get the system design any of
the mechanical design they're in
conversations where the legal regulatory
like brass tacks stuff about getting the
capacity to build it now that's very
cool
so practicality of that at the level of
you might call ontological design
architecture the physicality I feel like
we're a little bit behind the curve at
the level of the cultural side but not
radically trying to ramp it up with the
whole deal logos dialectic project and
and I think it's it's one of these
things were it's a matter of four
combinations it's mostly around finding
the people we've actually been holding
the other pieces and then beginning to
like you've got you got the core code
alright the core code of how do we
actually converse how do we connect how
do we actually begin to frame it bring
in the people and putting them in place
and then that should be expanding sphere
right it should be a network effect yeah
you're really good at getting the
actuality out of it not just the
potential so so those are like we've got
this practicality we're on the threshold
of actually being able to begin the
process of doing this thing I should
mention by the way that there's also
some really good work being done at the
level of socio technology like what are
the agreements and kind of fun things in
this weird transitionary period where
money is a key a key gating at it but
here's the flipside right
the flip side is the urgency or the
necessity of it was also quite present
growing and growing and me just kind of
like put a little bit of a well suppose
to to so when Paul was writing certainly
the
fall of room probably had a very felt
sense like like yeah the old way
definitely ain't sticking together like
that there was a Visser allottee to it
but they lacked the practicality and the
ability to actually get to the next
place was not they're not gonna get to
the moving in 880 but we now have booked
we have the felt sense of the urgency
and the thing we've been standing on is
sinking rapidly and on fire and they're
sharks and people are pulling it apart
and fill-in-the-blank and and and by the
way as you look around there's not like
a Western Europe and and Anatolia next
to us right is everywhere you look the
whole thing's on fire yeah alright so
that the urgency the fire the winch we
may not have intentionally consciously
chosen to set the ships on fire but the
ships are on fire and this notion of
practicality that the the ability to
reach up and grab that handhold and
begin to pull ourselves up is proximal
it's it's there it's do us yeah so so
both of those that we are now as far as
I know in a unique location I'm like
quite confident in a unique location in
the sum total of all history had his
characteristics and I want to say this
in a super super like banal way but I
found that it's been useful particularly
in talking with boomers superficially
this moment at the level of culture and
politics resembles that period in the
late 60s with which boomers were sort of
indelibly marked underground in Chicago
riots and crap like that but even a
little bit of fingernails scraping
reckoner feels the odor of
superficiality of it yeah yeah for
example in 1967 1969 almost the whole of
Western culture certainly the whole of
American culture was solid yeah this is
gigantic up upwelling of potential that
still hadn't even begun to slow down in
terms of its capacity to continue being
what it was like this huge inertial moon
and so while there was a breakdown going
on and that breakdown was significant
felt the level of race relationship
level of gender relationships and level
of culture in politics it was like a
little surface it's like a you know yeah
rocket ship entering into the atmosphere
was a fire here but the rest of the
rocket ship is in integrity this ain't
been right now the whole thing is on
fire all the way through pick any
institution there is no institution that
has a felt sense or a reality of
strength of competence of integrity of
resilience of duration but they all kind
of feel like they're doomed soon so so
on the one hand like things have not yet
gotten as hot as they were at the peak
of the 60s but we're now standing on
stilts not on a pillar yeah as they tip
over the consequences are vastly more
impactful than they were back then so
don't draw that metaphor or do draw the
metaphor then recognize that it's orders
and orders and orders of magnitude worse
and the metaphor would lead you to
believe
I agree thought right sorry I just felt
like that was gonna be a useful way of
just sort of connecting a few little
tiny dots yes that's why the metaphors I
use are the you know the Bronze Age
collapse the end of the Western Roman
Empire those are the ones that I'm using
and I even say this is even more radical
than what you're saying I think that
comparatively the French Revolution is
only scratching the surface of the
change in culture compared to the kind
of change we're facing right now right
now yes yeah right now exactly so we are
simultaneously proximal to stuff that we
can name like oh yeah it's like it's
like the 60s it's like the French
Revolution it's like the fall of Rome
yeah those are things that we can name
and some of us may actually have a felt
sense of what that means which is to say
right now like it's clearly proximal and
a whole lot bigger yeah I guess that's
that which go gun a lot all right no I
don't want to drain you just again this
has been really good and I think we
should towards what you said earlier
about you know getting the covers I
think getting the conversations going I
think the three of us you you and Greg
and I need to have a conversation or at
least a few around all of this because I
think there's very
there's adjacent possibilities that we
could very quickly actualize in the
discussion I think exactly I meant okay
well I'll be seeing you guys great
tomorrow I'll talk to him about it
tomorrow okay great
yeah let me know okay take good care my
friend you about right